Guide to the Bassett Affair Collection, 1903 - 2003
University Archives Duke University
Bassett Affair collection 1903 - 2003
Duke University. University Archives.
2.0 Linear Feet 300 Items
University Archives, Duke University
The Bassett Affair is a celebrated case that helped establish the concept of academic freedom in higher education in the United States and is a benchmark incident in race relations in the South. John Spencer Bassett, a Trinity College professor, published a series of articles in the South Atlantic Quarterly (1903) that praised the accomplishments of African Americans and offered views on how to improve race relations. A campaign to remove Bassett from the faculty was thwarted by a vote of support for Bassett from the University's Board of Trustees on Dec. 2, 1903. The collection contains essays, articles, clippings, correspondence, reminiscences, and other published and unpublished matter including Bassett's article, Stirring Up the Fires of Race Antipathy (1903); a scrapbook, 1903-1904, kept by Trinity College officials with newspaper clippings documenting national coverage the case received; copies of letters by Theodore Roosevelt to Owen Wister (1906) commenting on the case and on Trinity; manuscripts of My Recollections of the Bassett Trial, by Robert Lee Durham (1936), The Bassett Affair: A Play in Six Acts, by Baird Straughan (1975), and Crisis at Trinity a play by John Merritt (1989); lists of related materials in other collections; various shorter articles and speeches including comments by Richard L. Watson and an address to the Academic Council by Terry Sanford; and materials from the centennial celebration of the Bassett Affair, collected by University Archives staff.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
No restrictions.
Provenance
The Bassett Affair Collection was received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1979 (A79-39), 1996 (A96-2). University Archives staff added material about the centennial celebration of the Bassett Affair in 2003.
Historical Note
The Bassett Affair is a celebrated case that helped establish the concept of academic freedom in higher education in the United States and is a benchmark incident in race relations in the South. John Spencer Bassett, a Trinity College professor, published a series of articles in the South Atlantic Quarterly (1903) that praised the accomplishments of African Americans and offered views on how to improve race relations. A campaign to remove Bassett from the faculty was thwarted by a vote of support for Bassett from the University's Board of Trustees on Dec. 2, 1903.
Collection Overview
The collection contains essays, articles, clippings, correspondence, reminiscences, and other published and unpublished matter including Bassett's article, Stirring Up the Fires of Race Antipathy (1903); a scrapbook, 1903-1904, kept by Trinity College officials with newspaper clippings documenting national coverage the case received; copies of letters by Theodore Roosevelt to Owen Wister (1906) commenting on the case and on Trinity; manuscripts of My Recollections of the Bassett Trial, by Robert Lee Durham (1936), The Bassett Affair: A Play in Six Acts, by Baird Straughan (1975), and Crisis at Trinity a play by John Merritt (1989); lists of related materials in other collections; various shorter articles and speeches including comments by Richard L. Watson and an address to the Academic Council by Terry Sanford; and materials from the centennial celebration of the Bassett Affair, collected by University Archives staff.
Subject Headings
These and related materials may be accessed under the following subject headings in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.
Academic freedom
Bassett, John Spencer, 1867-1928
College teachers -- North Carolina
Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948
Duke University
Durham, Robert Lee, 1870-1949
Freedom of speech -- North Carolina
Historical drama, American -- North Carolina -- Durham
Racism -- North Carolina
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - John S. Bassett, Stirring Up the Fires of Race Antipathy, South Atlantic Quarterly, Oct. 1903, (copy) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Description of the John Spencer Bassett papers at the Library of Congress, 1995 (Folder 2)
  - Bassett Affair Scrapbook, 1903-1904, (copies) (Folder 3-5)
  - Robert Lee Durham, My Recollections of the Bassett Trial, 1936 (Folder 6)
  - E.C. Perrow, Report on the meeting of the Board of Trustees held on Dec. 1, 1903 (Folder 7)
  - Baird Straughan, The Bassett Affair: A Play in Six Scenes, [1975] (Folder 8)
  - John Merritt, Crisis at Trinity: A Play in Two Acts, 1989 (Folder 9)
  - Theodore Roosevelt's letters to Owen Wister, 1906, (copies) (Folder 10)
  - Harry Jackson's Reason Against Racism: A Primer on Academic Freedom, [1978], (manuscript) (Folder 11)
  - Correspondence and speeches (Folder 12)
  - Clippings (Folder 13-14)
  - Related material (Folder 15)
  - Centennial Celebration, 2003 (Folder 16)
    The centennial celebration of the Bassett Affair included a number of events held on the Duke University campus. This folder includes material collected by University Archives staff. It includes an article from the Herald Sun; a five part series of articles published in the Chronicle; a calendar of events; and speakers' notes from Robert Durden and William Chafe, who were part of a panel discussion entitled The Bassett Affair After a Century, sponsored by the History Dept.
  - Scrapbook of clippings related to the Bassett affair, 1903-1904, 62 pages (Box 2)
Related Material
John Spencer Bassett Papers.
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress.
John Spencer Bassett Papers.
University Archives, Duke University.
B.N. Duke Papers.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
John C. Kilgo Papers.
University Archives, Duke University.
James Southgate Papers.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.